League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia 033
People's Archive, MLK Library
League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia Records
1930-1982
People's Archive, MLK Library
League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia
033
22.5 Linear feet
31 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Topical Files, 1960-1979 (10 linear ft.) This series contains office files that contain correspondence, reports, proposals, newsletters, and programs on a variety of topics and issues of concern to the League. The series also contains files on the League's operations, including its by-laws, reports to the National League, and information on the League's Speakers Bureau. The series is further arranged chronologically into subseries. The first series covers Pre-1960 files with subsequent subseries generally covering one or two decades. Within each subseries, the folders are arranged alphabetically by topic. Subseries 1: Pre-1960 files, 1930-1960 (4.5 linear ft.) Significant topics included in the 1960 files are urban renewal, the Consumer's League, juvenile court law revision in the 1930s, recreation, urban housing, anti-discrimination, child welfare, foreign policy, and an all-day school proposal. Subseries 2: 1960-1969 files (4.5 linear ft.) Post-1960 topics include education, urban planning, the Metro Council, minimum wage, voter education, and election law reform. The files also contain files on international issues such as foreign relations and trade and opposition to totalitarian regimes. Subseries 3: 1970-1979 files (1 linear ft.) Files regarding the Potomac Metro Water Basin (1976-1979) and materials from a 1960 study of foreign relations with China are included in this subseries. Series 2: Clippings, 1960-1982 (2.5 linear ft.) This series contains clippings compiled by League members and staff regarding political issues of concern to the League. Home rule, the D.C. budget, D.C. public officials, civil rights, health, higher education, public schools, transportation, and taxes are only a few of the public policy issues covered by the clippings.
Biographical / Historical
As a result of the 19th Amendment that gave women the right to vote, the National League of Women Voters (NLWV) was established to educate women on how to vote and to provide information on public issues. On May 26, 1921, a meeting was called in the home of Mrs. Gifford Pinchot to form a District of Columbia branch of the National League of Women Voters. League charter members included Mrs. Frank Hiram Snell, Mrs. J. Borden Harriman, Mrs. Grace Chamberlain, Judge Mary O'Toole, Miss Harleen James, and Mrs. Elizabeth Brownlow. Famous members of the League have included First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt and Mrs. A.J. McKelway, wife of Benjamin McElway, who became editor of the Washington Evening Star in 1947. In 1926, the League adopted the name, "The Voteless District of Columbia League of Women Voters," to emphasize the District's disenfranchisement. Since its inception, the League's primary focus has been to educate and lobby for greater self-government for the citizens of the District. The D.C. League has worked on a variety of issues important to the District as well as national and international issues supported by the NWLV. During the 1930s and 1940s, the League conducted studies regarding public assistance relief and child welfare in the District, supported home front mobilization efforts during World War II, D.C. government reorganization, juvenile court changes, child labor laws, the 40-hour work week, and improvement of D.C. schools. Starting in the 1940s, the League began working for better race relations and supporting civil rights in the Nation's capital. The League supported desegregating District schools, and anti-discrimination laws in federal government employment and housing. In the 1950s and 1960s the League focused much of its attention on D.C. suffrage and home rule. By the 1980s, the League had positions on a number of public policy issues such as support of Advisory Neighborhood Commissions (ANCs), a rapid rail system, urban planning, Equal Rights Amendment ratification, and gun control laws with qualified support for the University of the District of Columbia and statehood for the District. The League prints a Voters Guide each election, sponsors a speakers bureau, conducts political debates, and advocates for a number of public policy issues for all D.C. citizens.
Custodial History
The Library received its first donation of records from the League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia in 1981 from Sue Panzer, President of the League. Subsequent donations have been received periodically from League members.
Related Materials
Internal Collection 001: Julius Hobson Papers (1960-1977) Collection 009: Harry S. Wender Papers (1930-1973) Collection 048: District of Columbia Statehood Commission Records (1788-1994) Collection 055: Home Rule Committee Collection (1939-1961) Collection 089: Martha McNeil Hamilton Collection (1971-1997)
External DC History Center: E1670, League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia Ephemera Collection George Washington University, Special Collections Research Center: MS 2326, Helen Halbig Papers
Scope and Contents
The collection contains clippings and alphabetically arranged office files maintained by the League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia to document its activities. Topics in the records cover primarily local D.C. political issues, but also national and international concerns of the National League of Women Voters. The records are divided into two series: topical files and clippings.
Civil rights; Politics and government; Statehood (American politics); Urban renewal; Gentrification; Home rule -- Washington (D.C.); Organizational Records; Associations, institutions, etc; Women; Suffrage
- Series 1: Topical Files, 1960-1979
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains office files that contain correspondence, reports, proposals, newsletters, and programs on a variety of topics and issues of concern to the League. The series also contains files on the League's operations, including its by-laws, reports to the National League, and information on the League's Speakers Bureau. The series is further arranged chronologically into subseries. The first series covers Pre-1960 files with subsequent subseries generally covering one or two decades. Within each subseries, the folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Subseries 1: Pre-1960 files, 1930-1960
    Significant topics included in the 1960 files are urban renewal, the Consumer's League, juvenile court law revision in the 1930s, recreation, urban housing, anti-discrimination, child welfare, foreign policy, and an all-day school proposal.
    - All Day School thru Anti-discrimination, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Benefits thru Congressional roll calls, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Consumers' League thru Fiscal policy: U.S., Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Finances, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Juvenile court thru Liberties, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Leadership training thru LWV National Council, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - National program, 1938-1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Office activities thru Publicity, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Public relations thru Publications, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Recreation thru Urban planning and housing, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Urban renewal thru welfare, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: 1960-1969 files
    Post-1960 topics include education, urban planning, the Metro Council, minimum wage, voter education, and election law reform. The files also contain files on international issues such as foreign relations and trade and opposition to totalitarian regimes.
    - Anti-discrimination thru Citizen involvement, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - D.C. budget thru D.C. government statistics, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - D.C. Government revenues thru Education Committee reports, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Education: higher thru Education, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Employment thru Human resources, 1961-1965 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - International relations thru lobbying, Undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Metro Council thru Observer Corporation, 1959-1966 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Positions thru Speakers Bureau, Undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Urban planning and housing, 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Voters' services: election laws thru Welfare, Undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 3: 1970-1979 files
    Files regarding the Potomac Metro Water Basin (1976-1979) and materials from a 1960 study of foreign relations with China are included in this subseries.
    - China study material, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Potomac Metro Water Basin, 1976-1979 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Clippings, 1960-1982
  This series contains clippings compiled by League members and staff regarding political issues of concern to the League. Home rule, the D.C. budget, D.C. public officials, civil rights, health, higher education, public schools, transportation, and taxes are only a few of the public policy issues covered by the clippings.
  - Untitled, 1960-1968 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1969-1971 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1972-1973 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1974-1977 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1978-1979 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1980-1981 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 1)